Guide to the National Grange of the Patrons of Husbandry records, 1842-1994
National Grange of the Patrons of Husbandry records, 1842-1994
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
National Grange of the Patrons of Husbandry records, 1842-1994.
3020
National Grange of the Patrons of Husbandry.
64 cubic ft.
Manuscripts, typescripts, bound volumes, clippings, photographs, slides, ribbons and medals.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Includes the files of National Masters and other Grange officials, the Executive Committee, and the Diamond Jubilee Building Fund. Material concerning the administration of the national and state granges, other agricultural organizations, farm credit, insurance, bonding, prices and price control, parity, taxation, Grange history, conferences, the "National Grange Monthly", and the building of the National Grange headquarters. Also included are personal papers of William Saunders, horticulturist, landscape architect, and first National Master; and personal papers of Oliver H. Kelley, founder and first National Secretary.
ORGANIZATIONAL HISTORY
The National Grange was founded in 1867 by Oliver Hudson Kelley as a political advocate for farmers and a cultural and social bastion of rural life.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Includes the files of Albert S. Goss (1924-1951) and Herschel D. Newsom (1943-1958), National Masters; Charles B. Bowling (1938-1966), Transportation Consultant; Lloyd C. Halvorson (1941-1957), Economics Consultant; C.W. "Jack" Jackson (1948-1961), Public Relations Director; Wib Justi (1949-1967), Director of Youth Services; the Executive Committee (1867-1959); and the Diamond Jubilee Building Fund (1940-1942). Consists of correspondence, memoranda, notes, financial records, minutes, agenda, constitution and bylaws, resolutions, reports, speeches, certificates, legislative bills, clippings, pamphlets, a volume of Grange melodies, a scrapbook, photographs, and broadsides concerning the administration of the national and state granges, other agricultural organizations, farm credit, insurance, bonding, prices and price control, parity, taxation, Grange history, conferences, the "National Grange Monthly", and the building of the National Grange headquarters.
Also included are personal papers (1847-1929) of William Saunders, horticulturist, landscape architect, and first National Master, consisting of correspondence, a diary, journals, notes, articles, pamphlets, scrapbooks, plans, sketches, stereoscopic slides, photographs, and memorabilia regarding the U.S. Experimental Gardens, the introduction of new plants to the U.S., his designs for the national cemetery at Gettysburg, the grounds of the Lincoln Monument at Springfield, Illinois,U.S. Department of Agriculture exhibits at various international exhibitions, and the National Grange; and personal papers (1842-1926) of Oliver H. Kelley, founder and first National Secretary, consisting of correspondence, notes, newspaper clippings, and memorabilia regarding the U.S. Department of Agriculture, the National Grange, and the Kelley family.
Correspondents include D. Wyatt Aiken, Spencer F. Baird, Patrick Barry, Roy Battles, Ezra T. Benson, Earl L. Butz, Harry B. Caldwell, Horace Capron, Richard C. Carrick, Roscoe Conkling, C. Jerome Davis, Dwight D. Eisenhower, Charles M. Gardner, C.M. Hall, Alvin E. Hanson, L. James Harmanson, Jr., T. Harvey Hedgepeth, Harold E. Heldreth, John D. Hervey, Warren G. Magnuson, Thomas Meehan, Isaac Newton, Franklin C. Nixon, Richard M. Nixon, Franklin D. Roosevelt, William H. Seward, E.R. Shankland, George A. Smathers, John W. Stokes, W. Stuart Symington, Louis J. Taber, George Thurber, Luther C. Tibbets, Mortimer Whitehead, William Whitsitt, and Oliver F. Winchester.
SUBJECTS
Names:
National Grange of the Patrons of Husbandry.; Aiken, David Wyatt, 1828-1887.; Baird, Spencer Fullerton, 1823-1887.; Barry, Patrick, 1816-1890.; Battles, Roy.; Benson, Ezra Taft, 1899- .; Bowling, Charles B.; Butz, Earl L.(Earl Lauer), 1909-; Caldwell, Harry B.; Capron, Horace, 1812-1885.; Carrick, Richard C.; Conkling, Roscoe, 1829-1888.; Davis, C. Jerome.; Eisenhower, Dwight D.(Dwight David), 1890-1969.; Gardner, Charles M.(Charles Milo), b. 1872.; Goss, Albert S. 1882-1950.; Hall, C.M.; Halvorson, Lloyd C.; Hanson, Alvin E., 1902-1965.; Harmanson, L. James, Jr.; Hedgepeth, T. Harvey.; Heldreth, Harold E.; Hervey, John D., 1888-1955.; Jackson, C.W. 1889-1966.; Justi, Wib.; Kelley, Oliver H.(Oliver Hudson), 1826-1913.; Magnuson, Warren Grant, 1905- .; Meehan, Thomas, 1826-1901.; Newsom, Herschel D. 1905- .; Newton, Isaac, 1800-1867.; Nixon, Franklin C.; Nixon, Richard M.(Richard Milhous), 1913- .; Roosevelt, Franklin D.(Franklin Delano), 1882-1945.; Saunders, William, 1820-1900.; Seward, William Henry, 1801-1872.; Shankland, E.R.; Smathers, George Armistead, 1913- .; Stokes, John Wesley, 1897- .; Symington, W. Stuart(William Stuart), 1901- .; Taber, Louis J., 1871-1960.; Thurber, George, 1821-1890.; Tibbets, Luther C.; Whitehead, Mortimer, 1841-1922.; Whitsitt, William Heth, 1841-1911.; Winchester, Oliver Fisher, 1810-1880.; United States.Experimental Gardens.; United States.Dept. of Agriculture.
Titles:
NATIONAL GRANGE MONTHLY.
Subjects:
Agriculture--Societies, etc.; Agricultural price supports.; Agricultural prices.; Horticulture--Societies, etc.
Form and Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; Constitutions.; Bylaws (administrative records); Minutes (administrative records)
INFORMATION FOR USERS
NATIONAL MASTERS
1
William Saunders, 1867-1873
2
Dudley W. Adams, 1873-1875
3
John T. Jones, 1875-1877
4
Samuel E. Adams, 1877-1879
5
Jonathan J. Woodman, 1879-1885
6
Israel Putnam Darden, 1885-1888
7
James Draper, 1888
8
Joseph H. Brigham, 1888-1897
9
Aaron Jones, 1897-1905
10
Nahum J. Bachelder, 1905-1911
11
Oliver Wilson, 1911-1919
12
Sherman J. Lowell, 1919-1923
13
Louis J. Taber, 1923-1941
14
Albert S. Goss, 1941-1950
15
Henry D. Sherwood, 1950
16
Herschel D. Newsom, 1950-1968
17
John W. Scott, 1968-
SERIES LIST
Series I. William Saunders
Boxes 1-8
Series II. O. H. Kelley
Box 7
Series III. National Grange; State Granges
Boxes 8-9
Series IV. Grand Master - Albert S. Goss
Box 11
Series V. Herschel D. Newsom
Boxes 12-13
Series VI. Diamond Jubilee Building Fund
Boxes 14-15
Series VII. Transportation Consultant - Charles Bowling
Boxes 15-18
Series VIII. Economist - Lloyd C. Halvorson
Boxes 19-20
Series IX. Public Relations Director - C. W. "Jack" Jackson
Boxes 20-25
Series X. Director of Youth Activities - Wib Justi
26-29
Series XI. Books, Journals, Articles
Box 30
Series XII. National Grange Ribbons, Medals, Buttons
Box 31
Series XIII. State Quarterly Reports
Box 32
Series XIV. National Quarterly Reports
Boxes 33, 34, 36
Series XV. Sixty Year Certificates
Box 35
Series XVI. Golden Sheaf Certificates
Boxes 37-39
Series XVII. Herschel D. Newsom testimonies, speeches, etc.
Box 40
Series XVIII. Peace Corps - Guatemala
Box 41
Series XIX. Consultant - Charles Bowling
Boxes 44-45
Series XX. Youth Department
42-43, 45-46
Series XXI. H. L. Graham files
Boxes 47-50
Series XXII. Miscellaneous Transportation
Box 51
Series XXIII. Commodity and dairy files
Boxes 52-53
Series XXIV. National legislative files
Boxes 54-64
Series XXV. Miscellaneous
Boxes 65-70
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. National Master - William Saunders 1867-1873
  - Letter register (v.b.), 1862-1865 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letter register (v.b.), 1865-1870 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letter register memoranda (of business in connection as Chair of Executive Committee), 1862, 1873 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Unidentified list of names, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1850-1859 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Includes Patrick Barry, Johns Hopkins, Thomas Meehan, Oliver F. Winchester, M. Russell Thayer.
  - Correspondence, 1859, 1860 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Includes Oliver F. Winchester, John Wesley Hoyt, Thomas P. James, Thomas W. Field, W. E. Taylor
  - Correspondence, 1867-1873 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Includes Isaac Newton, Charles McDonough, Patrick Barry, Luther Tucker, Henry Shaw, H. D. Emery, U.S. Patent Office (Agricultural Division), Department of City Property (Philadelphia), Missouri Botanical Garden, The Country Gentleman, Mount Hope Nurseries, The Prairie Farmer.
  - Correspondence, Apr. 1863 - Feb. 1864 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Includes Charles Sumner, Henry Shaw, Richard C. McCormick, Christopher Zugg, Charles M. Wetherill, William S. Sullivant, Steven L. Goodale, Charles M. Hovey, Henry R. Elliot, Norman J. Colman, Missouri Botanical Garden.
  - Correspondence, Mar. 1864 - July 1865 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Includes William R. Prince, Thomas P. James, John W. Forney, Grinnell.
  - Correspondence, Oct. 1865 - May 1867 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Includes John T. Stuart, H. R. Robey, Shelby M. Cullom, Edmund Morris, William H. Seward.
  - Correspondence, June 1867 - 1868 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Includes John W. Stokes, Horace Capron, William C. Cattell, D. A. Robertson (North Star Grange), Oliver H. Kelley, Department of Agriculture (U.S.), Minnesota Monthly.
  - Correspondence, 1869-1871 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Includes Thomas B. Bryan, Roscoe Conkling.
  - Correspondence, June 1871 - Apr. 1872 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Includes Frederick Watts, John L. Worden, Spencer F. Baird, Oliver H. Kelley, Department of Agriculture (U.S.), United States Naval Academy.
  - Correspondence, May 1872-May 1873 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Includes Joseph Henry, Thomas Meehan, John B. Bowman, Smithsonian Institute, Kentucky University.
  - Correspondence, photograph, June 1873 - Dec. 1873 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Includes John R. Thompson, Marshall P. Wilder, Mrs. Horace Capron, Thomas Meehan, E. R. Shankland, Henry Carey Baird, National Grange.
  - Correspondence, Jan. 1874 - Apr. 1874 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Includes Henry Peterson, Thomas J. Durant, Thomas Taylor, R. H. Thomas, S. C. Lyford, Henry Carey Baird, Pennsylvania State Grange, Board on behalf of U.S. Executive Departments.
  - Correspondence, May 1874 - Oct. 1874 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Includes Thomas J. Durant, H. W. L. Lewis, E. R. Shankind, Francis Thomas, Dudley W. Adams, D. Wyatt Aiken, Louisiana State Grange, National Grange
  - Correspondence, Nov. 1874 - Jan 1875 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Includes Thomas Meehan, D. Wyatt Aiken, C. Edwards Lester, William H. Earle, James Swan, National Grange, Springler House, Sovereigns of Industry, Fremont Grange (Topeka); Letter of Jan. 25, 1875 from Pembroke Jones written on same letter of July 13, 1875 from John Stewart - located in Box 3 Folder 1
  - Correspondence, Feb. 1875 - June 1875 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Includes Pliney Freeman, A. B. Grosh, Mortimer Whitehead, C. Edward Lester, William G. Wayne, Horace H. Day, R. Q. Tenney, Globe Mutual Life Insurance Company, New Jersey State Grange, New York State Grange (Executive Committee), Springler House, Colorado State Grange.
  - Correspondence, July 1875 - Dec. 1875 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Includes Dudley T. Chase, William B. Evans, Samuel Mullen, John Stewart (w/ attached letter from Pembroke Jones Jan. 25, 1875), National Grange, Southern States Agricultural and Industrial Exposition.
  - Correspondence, Jan. 1876 - July 1876 (Box 3, Folder 2 (a, b))
    Includes Maria Howland, Spencer F. Baird, Alfred T. Goshorn, Board on Behalf of U.S. Executive Departments, International Exhibition.
  - Correspondence, Aug. 1876 - Oct. 1876 (Box 3, Folder 3 (a, b))
    Includes George Thurber, Spencer Baird, W. D. Brackenridge, American Agriculturalist, Kissena Nurseries (S. B. Parsons & Son), International Exhibition, Board on Behalf of U.S. Executive Depts, Smithsonian Institute.
  - Correspondence, Nov. 1876 - July 1877 (Box 3, Folder 4 (a, b))
    Includes Thomas Meehan, Spencer F. Baird, George Thurber, D. D. T. Moore, Emily E. Briggs, S. C. Lyford, Board on Behalf of U.S. Executive Depts.
  - Correspondence, Aug. 1877 - Mar. 1878 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Includes George Thurber, Thomas Meehan.
  - Correspondence, May 1878 - May 1879 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Includes Richard E. Kunge, D. D. T. Moore, Robert F. Rogers, George Husmann, Robert Manning, Florida State Grange, American Pomological Society.
  - Correspondence, June 1879 - Sept. 1880 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    Includes George Thurber, William Le Duc, Samuel M. Tracy, American Agriculturalist, Department of Agriculture (U.S.), Mississippi Valley Horticultural Society.
  - Correspondence, Oct. 1880 - 1881 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    Includes Theodore Cuyler, J. J. Woodman, C. Edward Lester, Frederick Watts, George B. Loring, National Grange, National Journal, Department of Agriculture (U.S.).
  - Correspondence, 1882 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    Includes Charles W. Elliot, A. H. Manville, Marshall P. Wilder, B. C. Card, Thomas Meehan, American Pomological Society, Office of National Cemetaries, New York State Agricultural Experiment Station at Geneva, E. Lewis Sturtevant.
  - Correspondence, 1883- Aug. 1884 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    Includes Parker Earle, Thomas Meehan, Mississippi Valley Horticultural Society
  - Correspondence, Sept. 1884 - 1885 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    Includes Clara Barton, P. J. Berckman, J. J. Woodman, J. S. Tait, American Association of the Red Cross, National Grange.
  - Correspondence, 1886 - 1887 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    Includes Elias A. Long, Edmund H. Hart, Luther C. Tibbets, Isabel Mulford, Vassar College.
  - Correspondence, 1888-1891 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    Includes Thomas Meehan, A. N. Brown, George Thurber, R. H. Thomas, William A. Armstrong, Marshall I. Ludington, Delaware State Grange, Pennsylvania State Grange, New York State Grange, United States War Department.
  - Correspondence concerning 50th wedding anniversary, 1898 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, 1892, 1893, 1898, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 15)
    Includes D. Wyatt Aiken, John Hay, W. H. Stinson
  - Correspondence, autographs on landscape gardening, horticulture (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Diary (v.b.), 1897-1900 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Journal ("417") (v.b.), 1850-1859, 1861, 1862 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Journal (v.b.) on landscape gardening, 1855-1863 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Garden Journal & House Expenses (v.b.), 1858, 1861-1863 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Journal (v.b.) on U.S. Experimental Gardens, 1886-1898 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Journal (v.b.), 1898-1899 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    "Reminiscences of persons and things" - on National Cemetary, Washington D.C. (Capitol Terraces), and expositions
  - Travel journal (v.b.) - Florida, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Notes (v.b.) - botanical index (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Record of manuscript papers, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Photographs (v.b.) - pomologists, horticulturists, agriculturists, rural editors and indexes, 1863-1866 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Notes, clippings, prints on botany (v.b.), n.d. (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Notes, clippings (packages - Vol. 1), n.d. (Box 4, Folder 12 (a-d))
  - Botanical notes, clippings (packages - Vol. 2), n.d. (Box 4, Folder 13 (a-d))
  - Horticultural, scientific notes, articles, sketches (v.b.), C. 1847 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Stereoscopic slides (package) - mostly U.S Dept. of Ag. buildings, Wash. D.C., 1881 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - "Remarks on Grape Culture, with reference to mildew, both on the native and foreign varieties" (Report to the Commissioner of Patents), 1861 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - "Memoranda of Articles Received at the U.S. Experimental Garden with remarks by William Saunders Superintendent, 1862 " (v.b.), 1862-1882 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - "Shelter and Protection of the Orchards" (Report of the Commissioner of Agriculture), 1862 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - "Report of the Superintendent of the Garden attached to the Department of Agriculture" (Report of the Commissioner of Agriculture), 1862 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - "Report of the Superintendent of the Experimental Garden" (Report of the Commissioner of Agriculture), 1863 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - "Report of the Superintendent of the Experimental Garden" (Report of the Commissioner of Agriculture), 1864 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - "Report of the Superintendent of Gardens" (Report of the Commissioner of Agriculture), 1865 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - "Remarks on Pruning and Training the Grapevine with Quotations and Illustrations from Various Authors" (Report of the Commissioner of Agriculture), 1866 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - "Report of the Superintendent of the Experimental Garden" (Report of the Commissioner of Agriculture), 1866 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - "Report of the Superintendent of the Experimental Garden" (Report of the Commissioner of Agriculture), 1867 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - "Mildew on the Grape", 1867 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    A paper read at the meeting of the American Pomological Society at St. Louis (Monthly Reports of Department of Agriculture.)
  - "Report of the Superintendent of Gardens and Grounds" (Report of the Commissioner of Agriculture), 1868 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - "Hints in Horticulture: Hedges and Hedge Plants" (Report of the Commissioner of Agriculture), 1868 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - "Remarks on Pear Culture" (Report of the Commissioner of Agriculture), 1869 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - "Landscape Gardening" (Report of the Commissioner of Agriculture), 1870 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - "Report of the Superintendent of Gardens and Grounds" (Report of the Commissioner of Agriculture), 1870 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - "Report of the Superintendent of Gardens and Grounds" (Report of the Commissioner of Agriculture), 1871 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - "Report of the Superintendent of Gardens and Grounds" (Report of the Commissioner of Agriculture), 1876 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Reports, Division of Gardens and Grounds (U.S. Department of Agriculture), 1876, 1877, 1883 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Drafts of Reports of the Department of Agriculture, Division of Gardens and Grounds (U.S. Department of Agriculture), 1877, 1883 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - "Report of the Superintendent of Gardens and Grounds" (Report of the Commissioner of Agriculture), 1881, 1882 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - "Report of the Superintendent of Gardens and Grounds" (Report of the Commissioner of Agriculture), 1891 (Box 5, Folder 22 (a, b))
  - "Report of the Superintendent of Gardens and Grounds" (Report of the Secretary of Agriculture), 1893 (Box 5, Folder 23 (a, b, c))
  - "Report of the Chief of the Division of Gardens and Grounds" (Message and Documents, Department of Agriculture), 1895 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - "Report of the Superintendent of Experimental Gardens and Grounds" (Annual Reports of the Department of Agriculture), 1898 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Draft of Report on Fibre Plants, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 26 (a, b))
  - "Report of the Superintendent of Gardens and Grounds", 1889 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    Includes m.c. pages of "Report of the Superintendent of Gardens and Grounds", Report of the Secretary of Agriculture.
  - Reports of the Superintendent of Gardens and Grounds (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - "Remarks on the Design for the Soldier's National Cemetary", n.d. (Box 6, Folder 3)
    Also description of original design of the grounds of the Smithsonian Institute.
  - Reports and Descriptions of Landscape Designing (manuscripts, plans, map sketches), 1857, 1858, 1861 (Box 6, Folder 4 (a, b))
  - Drafts of Articles on Landscape Gardening and Design (Box 6, Folder 5 (a, b))
  - Drafts of Articles and Notes on Landscape Gardening (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Drafts of Article on Grape Culture and American Wines (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Drafts of Articles on Grape Culture: "Mildew", "Grape Culture in Cold Graperies", n.d. (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Drafts of Articles on Mildew and Grape Culture, Pot Culture of Grapes, Effects of Climate on Grapes (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Description of tour of vineyards and wine companies (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Draft of Article on Wine Grapes, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - "Culture of Exotic Grapes", n.d. (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Drafts of Articles on Grape Culture, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Drafts of Articles: "Cassia", "Cinnamon", "Vanilla", n.d. (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Drafts of Articles: "Orris Root", "Violet", n.d. (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Descriptions of Economic Trees and Plants (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Descriptions of Trees, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Drafts of Articles on Tree Culture: Planting and Pruning (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Notes on Tree Culture, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Drafts of Articles and Notes on Glass Houses (Greenhouse plants, Cold Grapery, Orchard House Culture) (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Notes on Employment of Gardeners, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous Notes on Fruit Tree Culture, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Horticultural Calendars, 1849 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - "Old Manuscript" on "Food of Plants", "Soil", "Potting", "Watering", "Temperature", 1852 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous Notes and Articles on Horticulture, 1859 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous Notes and Articles on Horticultural Subjects (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Drafts of Articles: How to grow native wild flowers; Winter Protection of Plants, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Drafts of Articles on the Sunflower and "A New Forage Plant" (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Drafts of Articles on: "Rockwork in Gardens", "Rose Beds", some flowering plants, and "Vegetable Manures" (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Draft of Article on Floriculture, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Draft of Article "Flower Gardens", n.d. (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Draft of Paper: "Horticultural Education", n.d. (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Draft of Descriptions of Exhibits at Philadelphia International Exhibition, 1876 (Box 7, Folder 13 (a, b))
  - "Notes for address on leaving the chair of Progressive Gardeners Society, Philadelphia", 1860 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Draft of Paper: "Heating Glass Structures" for Pennsylvania Horticultural Society, 1862 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Miscellaneous Reports and Paper for Horticultural Societies (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - "Prospectus of the American Workers' Alliance, for the Advancement of Educational, Industrial, Co-operative, and Social Reform" by Elizabeth Thompson and William Saunders, 1879 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Miscellaneous Notes and Articles not related to Horticulture (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - "An Account of the Orangeries and Irrigation of Blidah" by Ch. Joly., 1887 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Miscellaneous Articles and Notes (not Saunders' writing), 1893 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Translation: "Observation on the Florescence of Fruit Trees" by M. Eugene Forney, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - International Exhibition, 1876 - contracts, reports, invoices, plan, circular, notices, news clippings, 1874, 1875 (Box 7, Folder 22 (a, b))
  - Notes, m.c. circulars, 1876 (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Memorabilia (photographs, newsclippings, etc.), 1874, 1884, 1888 (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - Ledger (v.b.), 1855-1859 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Manuscript ledger (v.b.), 1856-1858 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Rent receipts (package), 1866-1879 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Cash book (v.b.), 1855-1857 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Address book, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Address book (v.b.), n.d. (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Newspaper articles (scrapbook), 1881, 1882 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Newspaper articles, correspondence (scrapbook), c. 1850-1900 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Newspaper clippings (scrapbook), 1849-1892 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Adlum, John. A Memoir on the Cultivation of the Vine in America and the Best Mode of Making Wine. Washington: William Greer., 1828 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - The Rural Annual and Horticultural Directory for the Year 1858. Rochester: Joseph Harris. (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Dreer, Henry A. Dreer's Garden Calendar for 1862. Philadelphia: A. M. Spangler. (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - The Prairie Farmer Annual for 1871. (pamphlet) Chicago: Prairie Farmer Company. (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Henderson, Peter, William Bennett, S. B. Parsons. Horticultural Essays., 1880 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    Essays read before the New York Horticultural Society in 1880. New York: Sears and Cole.